<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>politics on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/categories/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in politics on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Atheist prayer</title>
      <link>/post/on-gun-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/on-gun-love/</guid>
      <description>we fear the people who love their guns more than we love our children.
the atheist prays every day to gods she finds incomprehensible:
Remove the sticks of destruction from our arsenals and minds. Banish them to eternity. Cleanse us that we may be clean.
a merciful god would hear this supplicant, know her grace,  and answer in the affirmative. a god who loved his children would, she thinks and hopes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Donocrats and Trumpublicans</title>
      <link>/post/of-donocrats-and-trumpublicans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/of-donocrats-and-trumpublicans/</guid>
      <description>I wish it were otherwise, but I agree with Andrew Sullivan. Regardless of what the Mueller report holds, Trump has severely damaged the country and made our Nation weaker, not stronger.
Regretably, Mr. Trump has been exactly the sort of president many of us feared he would be. And his supporters, Donocrat and Trumpublican alike, actually like it that way. That is the grim reality that his opponents must face. His bombast and bluster and poutiness and pettiness appeal to large numbers of Americans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>April 9: A national day of reflection and reconciliation</title>
      <link>/post/april-9-a-day-of-reflection-and-reconciliation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/april-9-a-day-of-reflection-and-reconciliation/</guid>
      <description>America needs a holiday dedicated to reflecting on the many ways we have failed to meet our founding ideals. We need such a holiday to reconcile the past with our common hopes for a better future, to &amp;lsquo;bind up the Nation&amp;rsquo;s wounds&amp;rsquo;, as Lincoln suggested in his second inaugural address. I suggest we make April 9 that day.
Lee surrendered to Grant on April 9, 1865 in Appomattox Court House, Virginia, a month after Lincoln&amp;rsquo;s second inaugural.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ending the endless war</title>
      <link>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</guid>
      <description>I find Andrew Sullivan worth reading almost all of the time even if I disagree with him. This time, I agree completely:
 &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;I simply do not believe that the West has the knowledge, the will, or the ability to shape the extremely complicated and endlessly vicious politics of the Middle East. And I defy anyone to show otherwise&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;
 So, while I find the present occupant completely unfit for office, I applaud his announcement to withdraw U.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>