<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>research | Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/category/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>research</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>research</title>
      <link>/category/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameters for action</title>
      <link>/post/parameters-for-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/parameters-for-action/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, Florian Raudies, Swapnaa Jayaraman and I published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/DEVLRN.2015.7345450&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; where we simulated the optic flow that infants would experience in different head/body postures.
We computed cyclopian (one-eyed) flow on the basis of this schematic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gilmore-lab/temple-2017-02-27/master/img/computing-flow.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, the key parameters were the instantaneous translation &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\((v_x{}, v_y{}, v_z{})\)&lt;/span&gt; and rotation &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\((\omega_{x}, \omega_y{}, \omega_z{})\)&lt;/span&gt; of the planar retina.
Coupled with the optic flow equation,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\begin{pmatrix}\dot{x} \\ \dot{y}\end{pmatrix}=\frac{1}{z} \begin{pmatrix}-f &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; x\\ 0 &amp;amp; -f &amp;amp; y \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix}{v_x{}}\\ {v_y{}} \\{v_z{}}\end{pmatrix}+ \frac{1}{f} \begin{pmatrix} xy &amp;amp; -(f^2+x^2) &amp;amp; fy\\ f^2+y^2 &amp;amp; -xy &amp;amp; -fy \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} \omega_{x}\\ \omega_{y}\\ \omega_{z} \end{pmatrix}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we were able to simulate the &lt;em&gt;perceptual&lt;/em&gt; effects of postural geometry: Changes in eye height and forward translational speed that would occur when a child changed from crawling to walking altered the pattern of retinal flow &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\((\dot{x}, \dot{y})\)&lt;/span&gt; in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work has lain dormant for a few years, but I now want to pick it back up.
In short, there are a handful of perception/action systems that provide the nervous system with deterministic, causal information about the effects of different actions.
These must be important for development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next step, I’m looking for a concise, but thorough parameterization of body posture that includes the eyes, head, torso, arms, and legs.
Here’s a sketch of what I have in mind for the upper parts body that have the greatest impact on the direction of visual fixation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Body part&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Parameter(s)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eyes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$&lt;em&gt;{rx}, &lt;/em&gt;{ry}, &lt;em&gt;{lx}, &lt;/em&gt;{lx} $&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Head&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\theta_x{}, \theta_y{}, \theta_z{}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Torso&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$_x{}, _y{}, _z{} $&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coupled with the distance between the eyes, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;, the radial distance to the head’s center of rotation, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(h\)&lt;/span&gt;, and the distance from the head’s center of rotation to the torso’s center of rotation, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt;, we can compute the effects of eye, head, and torso movement on visual motion at the two retinae.
Now, if the &lt;em&gt;visual&lt;/em&gt; signals from eye vs. head vs. torso can be distinguished, then these could couple with other proprioceptive (muscle, tendon, cutaneous) signals to provide a powerful set of &lt;em&gt;sensory&lt;/em&gt; signals that are directly caused by eye, head, and torso motion.
See &lt;a href=&#34;../the-webs-we-weave/&#34;&gt;this earlier post&lt;/a&gt; for a causal graph that elaborates on this point.
I’ll discuss why I think there are &lt;em&gt;visual&lt;/em&gt; differences in the effects of eye and head motion in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next step is to ask my colleagues in kinesiology if there is a canonical parameterization of body position that I can build upon.
If you know of one, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New lab logo</title>
      <link>/post/new-lab-logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-lab-logo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For I don&amp;rsquo;t remember how many years I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted a lab logo.
I thought that designing a logo was something that &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; student might actually enjoy doing.
But I never pushed or insisted, and so it never happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, as a byproduct of a bunch of reading I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing about causal modeling and the philosophy of science, I came up with a figure that seems to work on several levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../img/nested-causality.jpg.png&#34; height=150px/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outer circle represents the world, the next circle the body that is embedded in the world, the next the nervous system embedded in that body (in the world), and the smallest the mind embedded in the brain (in the body in the world).
The world, body, and brain are directly measurable in various ways.
The mind is not.
We infer properties and structures of the mind indirectly, through patterns of brain activity or peripheral physiology or behavior.
The focal point of psychology as a science is making inferences about something that cannot be directly measured.
This is one reason psychology is harder than physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure has other associations.
It is similar to one used to demonstrate that rotational motion in 2 dimensions can evoke the perception of an object in 3 dimensions &amp;ndash; something called the stereokinetic depth effect (SKE).
It evokes the perception of a cone-like shape protruding up and to the left.
And it evokes a weaker perception of a tunnel.
I study depth perception and motion perception, so these features make the figure even more appealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the figure could be viewed as a large letter O, for openness, something I now embrace in all aspects of my scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I confess that I was just trying a new way to depict the embedded causal relationships among mind, brain, body, and the environment and found a color scheme I liked.
The rest was purely accidental.
But I guess invention is like that sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you like it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
