<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>science on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/categories/science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in science on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavior is the linchpin</title>
      <link>/post/behavior-is-the-linchpin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/behavior-is-the-linchpin/</guid>
      <description>The Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute for Child Health and Human Development (NICHD) has requested input on a draft strategic plan for 2020-2024.
NICHD supports Databrary and PLAY, and it has supported my habituation modeling work in the past. The following is a draft response my colleagues and I are working on.
Dear Dr. Bianchi:
Thank you for the opportunity to respond to the NICHD Strategic Plan for Fiscal Years 2020-2024.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In search of the ethogram</title>
      <link>/post/in-search-of-the-ethogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/in-search-of-the-ethogram/</guid>
      <description>Psychology is in part, a science of behavior. Mental experience &amp;ndash; thoughts and feelings &amp;ndash; are also common targets of inquiry.
I recently went looking for a systematic catalogue of behaviors that should, in theory, constitute the substance of what psychologists and other behavioral scientists study. My goal was to take that catalogue as a starting point for thinking about the relationship between information available for perception and the actions (behaviors) that this information informs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameters for action</title>
      <link>/post/parameters-for-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/parameters-for-action/</guid>
      <description>Several years ago, Florian Raudies, Swapnaa Jayaraman and I published a paper where we simulated the optic flow that infants would experience in different head/body postures. We computed cyclopian (one-eyed) flow on the basis of this schematic:
Here, the key parameters were the instantaneous translation \((v_x{}, v_y{}, v_z{})\) and rotation \((\omega_{x}, \omega_y{}, \omega_z{})\) of the planar retina. Coupled with the optic flow equation,
\(\begin{pmatrix}\dot{x} \\ \dot{y}\end{pmatrix}=\frac{1}{z} \begin{pmatrix}-f &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; x\\ 0 &amp;amp; -f &amp;amp; y \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix}{v_x{}}\\ {v_y{}} \\{v_z{}}\end{pmatrix}+ \frac{1}{f} \begin{pmatrix} xy &amp;amp; -(f^2+x^2) &amp;amp; fy\\ f^2+y^2 &amp;amp; -xy &amp;amp; -fy \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} \omega_{x}\\ \omega_{y}\\ \omega_{z} \end{pmatrix}\)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The webs we weave</title>
      <link>/post/the-webs-we-weave/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-webs-we-weave/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been ‘sketching’ out conceptual models for some time without realizing that there is an entire field of analysis where these sorts of diagrams are the starting point: Causal modeling. My introduction to this world was Judea Pearl’s The Book of Why: The New Science of Cause and Effect. Interested casual readers might also enjoy Steve Sloman’s excellent and delightfully clear Causal Models: How People Think About the World and Its Alternatives.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>