<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Outdoors</title>
      <link>/personal/adventure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/adventure/</guid>
      <description>For fun, I like to walk, run, hike, backpack, kayak and ride my bicycles: a foldable touring Bike Friday, a Specialized Hybrid that I sometimes use to commute to work, a Specialized Allez road bike, and stoker-willing, a road tandem we call Tonya. Last summer, my wife and I took a tour of southern Tuscany with Vermont Bicycle Tours (VBT).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arts</title>
      <link>/personal/arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/arts/</guid>
      <description>My family and I have been involved theatre and music for a very long time. Indeed, my wife and I met in a production of &amp;ldquo;South Pacific&amp;rdquo; with the Georgetown Gilbert &amp;amp; Sullivan Society (GG&amp;amp;SS).
Recent shows here in State College have included &amp;ldquo;Oliver!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Sound of Music,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Sweeney Todd,&amp;rdquo; with Singing Onstage, &amp;ldquo;Dracula&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Survivor&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Gypsy&amp;rdquo; with the State College Community Theatre (SCCT), and &amp;ldquo;The Memory of Water&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Harper Regan&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Two Can Play&amp;rdquo; with The Next Stage theatre company.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equipment</title>
      <link>/personal/ham_radio_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/ham_radio_2/</guid>
      <description> VHF/UHF  Kenwood TH-D74 HT Yaesu FT-70DR HT Kenwood TM-D710G mobile Kenwood TM-281 mobile (for APRS I-Gate) Tytera MD-2017 HT  HF  Icom IC-7300 MFJ 993B autotuner Multiband (80-10m) dipole at 10 m  Other  Tecsun PL-880 portable shortwave/medium wave receiver Openspot UHF digital mode (D-Star, Fusion, DMR) hotspot  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ham Radio</title>
      <link>/personal/ham_radio_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/ham_radio_1/</guid>
      <description>I was licensed as a Tech+ in 1993, but was never really active. Kids and finishing grad school were higher priorities. After reading &amp;ldquo;Seveneves,&amp;rdquo; I got the bug again and took both the Technician and General in the space of a couple of weeks in the summer of 2016. With the moral support of some fellow club members and a helpful Elmer, I upgraded to Extra in July of 2017.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heroics</title>
      <link>/personal/heroics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/heroics/</guid>
      <description>Some rascal or rogue Stashed kryptonite Upon my person.
Perhaps in that fingertip pocket of my Levi’s, Or the underside of the spare button on that green and black plaid shirt, Or the tunnel in my underwear that no man uses I assure you but most boys try at least once.
I have always loved flying And nerdy girls. I have been underestimated by villains, And see beneath the surfaces of things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public Service</title>
      <link>/personal/public_service/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/public_service/</guid>
      <description>I have been involved in local politics, serving as clerk and Judge of Elections in my State College precinct and now Majority Inspector. I was a moderate Republican at one point, but changed parties after the 2000 election.
My wife and I were formerly Democratic Precinct Co-chairs.
I&amp;rsquo;m especially proud of the work that led to the construction of the Bellefonte Central Rail Trail. It was one of our community&amp;rsquo;s constructive responses to 9&amp;frasl;11.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goad Gunner</title>
      <link>/personal/goad-gunner/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/goad-gunner/</guid>
      <description>taunts of bad hair boy-men transfix the play yard. mine is bigger. no mine. look.
there is no alternative channel for the cartoon among nations.
our smiley wiley has chased some tail feather off a cliff and stands now unbound by ground, animation suspended.
&amp;lsquo;tis only a matter of time until the forces of nature overcome their shock at the effrontery and shame gravity to reassert its inevitable grasp on matter and mass.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fourth and long</title>
      <link>/personal/fourth-and-long/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/fourth-and-long/</guid>
      <description>sometimes late in the 4th quarter you&#39;re down a score, out of timeouts, and it&#39;s 4th and long.
on the line is your whole season
or your job
or your life.
and you throw the Hail Mary toward that one corner of the endzone where your receivers just might beat the cornerbacks in a jump ball or a volleyball tip, and two feet just might land in bounds, and the crowd just might roar, and you just might reach to the sky in triumph, and your tears just might be ones of joy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Delightful delusion</title>
      <link>/personal/delightful-delusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/delightful-delusion/</guid>
      <description>oh my, yes. I oh so wanted to see a tuxedo, penguin crisp, satin shiny, pseudo-sparkle when he sauntered by us peons, clinging to such rags as misfortune left in her cloud of dust and tears. Coughing.
but, oh my no. no. Clad there not in finery, but in the simplest of suits. Birthday I am told the style. Flattered, but not flattering. Scoffing, not coughing.
And in seeing I could not unsee, despite I swear so wanting, you must believe, Nor in knowing could I unknow what what wisdom bears in its stoop and beard the penultimate emptiness of every emperor, penguin or man.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Promise</title>
      <link>/personal/promise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/promise/</guid>
      <description>I flare my talons and prepare to strike, but only in defense. I sharpen my beak, but only in warning.
I am your presidential detail, your Secret Service. Vigilant. Committed. I seek out bullets fired in your direction by indifferent snipers and absorb their impact with joy. Unwounded.
I will carry your heart when it cannot be lifted. I will find you when you are lost even to yourself. I will light your darkness with the fire in my eyes, and we will crawl together out of the wilderness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Specific gravity</title>
      <link>/personal/specific-gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/specific-gravity/</guid>
      <description>the call always comes too early in the morning for anything but mischief or the baker
I know who&#39;s talking but not the language spoken.
hand on the bannister does not steady. the direction of gravity skewed by other forces of nature.
there now is down, but which way up?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I never metaphysics</title>
      <link>/personal/i-never-metaphysics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/i-never-metaphysics/</guid>
      <description>it&#39;s like fireworks, dad. you said the colors and patterns come from all the minerals. their making a mutual arrangement designed to ignite and illuminate.  you said the designers crafted this one boomy blue and that one sparkly-white. this cascade brilliant, that smiley face a dud.  flying high or bursting low, it&#39;s all in the timing and atmospheric conditions. don&#39;t forget chemistry and physics. human ingenuity (and error).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haiku 4 U</title>
      <link>/personal/haiku-4-u/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/haiku-4-u/</guid>
      <description>One last time, Dad says. Jason squeals ands bolts inside the mister. Slippery guy.
The audacity of giant metal tin-men shames the humbler heart.
What are crab cheese fries? Regular with seasoning? Do they sell? Who knows?
The didgery-dude took a raincheck. See, honey, I should have bought one.
Nittany Lion mating calls echo &amp;lsquo;cross the Borough. Love me, do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lonely cicada</title>
      <link>/personal/lonely-cicada/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/lonely-cicada/</guid>
      <description>Lonely cicada. Bad at math. Off by one? Damn. No choral singing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh beautiful</title>
      <link>/personal/oh-beautiful/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/oh-beautiful/</guid>
      <description>sweet land of liberty of thee i sing
the world will little note, nor long remember what we say here, but it can never forget what they did: unreasonable searches and seizures deprived of life, liberty, or property without due process.
o say can you see by the dawn&#39;s early light that a house divided against itself cannot stand; that bravura is not bravery.
this land is your land, this land is my land.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Food for thought</title>
      <link>/personal/food-for-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/food-for-thought/</guid>
      <description>yes she cranked the handle but the meat and potato man put his heart in the grinder and no one saved the pink spaghetti strands for chili.
 he could have had his cake and eaten humble pie or worn it as a badge of honorable intent. instead he tasted just desserts that fate sandwiched between margaritaville and a cheeseburger in paradise.  full of gumption Forest&#39;s mother disparaged the integrity of chocolates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four letter word</title>
      <link>/personal/four-letter-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/four-letter-word/</guid>
      <description>I strangled hope. Smug bastard annoyed me. I spring eternal; there is always room for me, he&#39;d say (or his fanboys would moonily recite). So I grabbed his throat and fingers clenched squeezed. his eyes bulged green then withered gray. he lay dishrag limp on my lap. I hissed a firehose sigh, a contrail marking passage across some cloudless sky and felt don&#39;t laugh full of...
Persistent bastard. Kill you again if I have the chance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who knows how to unmake love</title>
      <link>/personal/who-knows-how-to-unmake-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/who-knows-how-to-unmake-love/</guid>
      <description>Who knows how to unmake love? that fertile ground for growing goodness in tiny cracks between beings. Passionate demands attention, but draws reluctant admiration for his gymnastic stamina and singularity of focus -- a laser light later scattered in time&#39;s gauze. Oh so cute I could pinch the cheeks of this Puppy she says 40 Years Married now. Others applaud politely if not quite aspiring to such longevity. Unrequited garners the requisite sympathy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lipstick on a pig</title>
      <link>/personal/lipstick-on-a-pig/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/lipstick-on-a-pig/</guid>
      <description>some Wilburs inspire no spider-poets nor earn the love of Fern.
this pig shuns lipstick. his countenance admits no adornment.
ears perky, hairs erect, nose for mayhem acute, undulled, taste for anything.  Orwell&amp;rsquo;s Napoleon commands our farm. cowed, we animals howl or growl assent to each assertion of fat cat dogma.  Ham? I am. you speak newspeak? come wallow in the mud and muck with me. it&amp;rsquo;s warm; you&amp;rsquo;re welcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unsolicited Advice</title>
      <link>/personal/unsolicited-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/unsolicited-advice/</guid>
      <description>My unicorn Is patron saint of regret. He holds dominion over Things wished-for but not received. the unfulfilled, unrequited, unrealized.
Get it? He says, I&#39;m like a Magritte or an Escher. Self-referential.
I don&#39;t. Or, I do, but I&#39;m wallowing.
Quite unselfservingly, He says I should shun the vaporous un.... and rather mind those things I got but did not think to wish for.
Treasure there, matey --  Forges to steel the metal in yer mettle; (He&#39;s fond of pirate talk, too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who shall lionize</title>
      <link>/personal/who-shall-lionize/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/who-shall-lionize/</guid>
      <description>who shall lionize this deceased? and where pray tell shall the bodiless be interred? i know not where to lay bouquets nor what color on such civic holy-days that celebrate my dear departed.  the stones i have accumulated to mark a graveside visit stack cold
hurl them at the walls of this always glass but newly transparent house of cards. shatter or bounce. who cares?  when dreams die the pain sears as befits that without which we choose not to endure  but must.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels Blue</title>
      <link>/personal/angels-blue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/angels-blue/</guid>
      <description>Gods I&amp;rsquo;ve always viewed with skepticism, But, I met an angel named Shirley.
They don&#39;t wear wings, you know. Impractical indoors. Hard to fit under a winter coat. Showy. Too many feathers ruffled already.
Or halos. Lord knows we have enough of those.
Sensible shoes? You bet. Got to keep their footing sure.
Craig or Suzanne might play a little trumpet, but only in the municipal band.
And none of them want to wrestle, ok?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Love of death</title>
      <link>/personal/love-of-death/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/love-of-death/</guid>
      <description>Love of death and fear of life well describes the current strife in Babylonia today. Nihilism rules the day. And what persuades the nihilist? Nothing, save the gun or fist. So, honor life -- with every breath speak words that counter love of death. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No one loves a volcano</title>
      <link>/personal/no-one-loves-a-volcano/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/no-one-loves-a-volcano/</guid>
      <description>spewing strangling gas red white vapor paints green grass gray.
unlovely lava flows -- entrails of eviscerated Earth --  that true when cool replenish tired soils.
and also true his indigestion soothed by some poison belch --  by gravity&#39;s hand sculpts the quieted cone into a shape most grand.
Still, I pity.
We misunderstand the flaming ash hole. We fear. We blame.
When it is the foul deep, Hades black bile, that forces its stench upward, ripping open his closed throat to spray things unwelcome here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The physics of love</title>
      <link>/personal/the-physics-of-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/the-physics-of-love/</guid>
      <description>like surfing a comet
in such a frictionless state we are thought experiments in Schrodinger&#39;s sanctuary, simultaneously alive and dead, both and neither, statistically speaking. let us out of the box to end the mystery; measure our true state at your peril and ours.
novices idealize its positions, velocities, accelerations of different centers of mass. meanwhile the conservation of momentum, the history of trajectories of particles in collision, demonstrates the superiority of this calculus over that algebra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Worn on the sleeve</title>
      <link>/personal/worn-on-the-sleeve/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/worn-on-the-sleeve/</guid>
      <description>I used to envy those who carried their hearts safe surrounded by the warm fellowship of other organs.
worn on the sleeve mine fits no item of clothing, so rides exposed, bumping into this sharp-edged tongue, or that pointed remark.
but a bleeding heart is never really broken, and worn there it escapes its ribbed-cage.
on the lam, its every beat sucks in sorrow, pumps out sweetness, the flow of life and its ebb.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There are no heroes</title>
      <link>/personal/there-are-no-heroes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/there-are-no-heroes/</guid>
      <description>there are no heroes in this comic book,
but everyone wears a costume, good guys and bad.
or worse a mask that fools none but mothers
who play along
complicit in their love.
at stake stands no less
the world,
the lives of innocents,
the child in distress.
super powers, super powerful
warp their wielder&amp;rsquo;s character
move mountains, oh yes, but
who, I ask who will remove the rubble?
we wear kryptonite because it is the fashion</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Burns a bridge</title>
      <link>/personal/we-do-not-swim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/we-do-not-swim/</guid>
      <description>burns a bridge the night long, this heat retards bitterness and cold yellow-red flickers illuminate, but dimly even in that moment fleeting but wonders he later wherefore the stench and who has shut the road again.
we do not swim.
in motion emotion forever forward fresh, frenetic, pushed by what i know not pulled more like perhaps by gravitational force or some repulsion. the formula admits no closed form solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joy untethered</title>
      <link>/personal/joy-untethered/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/joy-untethered/</guid>
      <description>joy untethered by sorrow
i mistrust.
twitches she there rootless,
buffeted by the mindless exhaltation of hope.
but anchored to sad
lightness soars,
stretches,
tugs at the reins of actual,
sending skyward
a kite of kindness.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>