<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rick Gilmore&#39;s site on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rick Gilmore&#39;s site on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Building walls and tearing them down</title>
      <link>/post/building-walls-and-tearing-them-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/building-walls-and-tearing-them-down/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The building of walls is of much concern these days.
This song from Anais Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s folk opera &amp;ldquo;Hadestown&amp;rdquo; sheds light on &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; some of us want so desperately to build them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8sQ8R54C53o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must also wonder what future Mexican leader will call on us to tear down the wall we seem so desperate to build?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GCO9BYCGNeY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walls are no symbol of strength.
They shut in more than they keep out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLAY project</title>
      <link>/project/play/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 16:55:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/play/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Play &amp;amp; Learning Across a Year (PLAY) project will provide a first-ever glimpse inside the homes of almost 1,000 families across the U.S.
We will collect, annotate (code), and openly share on &lt;a href=&#34;https://databrary.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Databrary&lt;/a&gt; video recordings of mothers and 12-, 18-, and 24-month-old infants engaged in natural behavior in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test-driven development is hard...and important.</title>
      <link>/post/test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I’ve been developing an R package that interacts with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://databrary.org&#34;&gt;Databrary.org&lt;/a&gt; API and with &lt;a href=&#34;https://datavyu.org&#34;&gt;Datavyu&lt;/a&gt; annotation files stored locally or on Databrary alongside shared videos. If you’re curious, you can download the &lt;code&gt;databraryapi&lt;/code&gt; package from this GitHub repository: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/PLAY-behaviorome/databraryapi&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/PLAY-behaviorome/databraryapi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many people in the software world, I’m entirely self-taught. Ok, I took a class in C programming at the U.S. Department of Agriculture’s Graduate School in the year before I applied to graduate schools in cognitive neuroscience. But my R package development skills are entirely self-taught. I must thank the incredibly generous geniuses who have gone before me and who share their code and their talents so freely and openly. Without the almost instant availability of these resources, my progress would be much, much slower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers are an opinionated bunch, and there are at least as many styles (fads?) in software development as their are developers. One style that I have started to try to emulate is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development&#34;&gt;‘test-driven development’&lt;/a&gt;. In TDD, the idea is that you create tests for how each part of your package should respond given this or that input. If your tests are through enough and correct, your package should work…at least within the boundaries of what you tested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the latest version of the package (0.1.4), I added a bunch of new tests to evaluate several new functions I’ve added to the package. Let’s just say that getting through my own self-designed test battery was challenging. But as a result, the code is cleaner and less buggy than it would be if I hadn’t gone this route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the larger sense, TDD is sort of a “plan for the worst” style. I like it because I know it forces me to be more precise and specific than I might otherwise choose to be. Since I’ve been using the &lt;code&gt;databraryapi&lt;/code&gt; more often for keeping tabs on what’s going on in the Databrary world, that’s a very good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you’re curious what the package can do, check this out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::install_github(&amp;quot;PLAY-behaviorome/databraryapi&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Skipping install of &amp;#39;databraryapi&amp;#39; from a github remote, the SHA1 (a6a700ea) has not changed since last install.
##   Use `force = TRUE` to force installation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of some recently authorized researchers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;databraryapi::get_db_stats(&amp;quot;people&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 6 x 6
##      id sortname   prename  affiliation                   url   institution
##   &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;      &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;                         &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; &amp;lt;lgl&amp;gt;      
## 1  4784 Steinbeis  Nikolaus University College London     &amp;lt;NA&amp;gt;  NA         
## 2  4794 Scheeringa Michael  Tulane University School of … &amp;lt;NA&amp;gt;  NA         
## 3  4776 Sansom     Jennifer Central Michigan University   &amp;lt;NA&amp;gt;  NA         
## 4  4790 Bloom      Stacie   New York University           &amp;lt;NA&amp;gt;  NA         
## 5  4692 Malti      Tina     University of Toronto         &amp;lt;NA&amp;gt;  NA         
## 6  4640 Fernandez  Victor   Georgetown University         &amp;lt;NA&amp;gt;  NA&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is a very simple plot of the growth in authorized researchers and institutions over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;with(databraryapi::read_csv_data_as_df(), plot(Auth_Investigators, Institutions))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## No encoding supplied: defaulting to UTF-8.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2018-12-28-test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve said in other places that I think scientists will eventually interact with their data programmatically – via scripts like this – with the data and materials stored in repositories that others can also access programmatically. Furthermore, I think that the philosophy of test-driven development can help make our software AND the results and findings we derive from it more robust and reproducible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethical data sharing</title>
      <link>/project/permission-to-share/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 14:31:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/permission-to-share/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Video recordings pose challenges for data sharing.
They contain faces and voices that cannot be easily eliminated or altered without harming the value of the recordings for other researchers.
My colleagues and I developed a data sharing policy framework for Databrary that requires researchers to gain consent to share from research participants and restricts access to institutionally-approved researchers.
Databrary&amp;rsquo;s template sharing release (permission) language may be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.databrary.org/resources/templates/release-template.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and some draft language relevant for gaining permission to share identifiable in the context of the EU&amp;rsquo;s General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) may be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gilmore-lab/ethical-data-sharing-w-GDPR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>databraryapi package</title>
      <link>/project/databraryapi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 12:52:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/databraryapi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have released a working version (0.1.4) of an R package that interacts with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://databrary.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Databrary.org&lt;/a&gt; API.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 12:37:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a break, I&amp;rsquo;m back to blogging using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;blogdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package for R, and the Hugo &lt;strong&gt;Academic&lt;/strong&gt; theme.
Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ending the endless war</title>
      <link>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I find Andrew Sullivan worth reading almost all of the time even if I disagree with him.
This &lt;a href=&#34;http://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/12/andrew-sullivan-establishment-will-never-say-no-to-a-war.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;time&lt;/a&gt;, I agree completely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;I simply do not believe that the West has the knowledge, the will, or the ability to shape the extremely complicated and endlessly vicious politics of the Middle East. And I defy anyone to show otherwise&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while I find the present occupant completely unfit for office, I applaud his announcement to withdraw U.S. troops from Syria and reduce our presence in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We forget that &lt;em&gt;Congress&lt;/em&gt; has the Constitutional power to declare war or decisively choose not to.
It&amp;rsquo;s part of the balance of powers created by the Framers.
I&amp;rsquo;d like to see Congress restore balance here and in other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Young children&#39;s neural processing of their mother’s voice: An fMRI study</title>
      <link>/publication/peep-ii-voices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/peep-ii-voices/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuroscience: The frontier within</title>
      <link>/talk/olli-2018-10-29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/olli-2018-10-29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outdoors</title>
      <link>/personal/adventure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/adventure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For fun, I like to walk, run, hike, backpack, kayak and ride my bicycles: a foldable touring Bike Friday, a Specialized Hybrid that I sometimes use to commute to work, a Specialized Allez road bike, and stoker-willing, a road tandem we call Tonya.
Last summer, my wife and I took a tour of southern Tuscany with Vermont Bicycle Tours (VBT).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arts</title>
      <link>/personal/arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My family and I have been involved theatre and music for a very long time.
Indeed, my wife and I met in a production of &amp;ldquo;South Pacific&amp;rdquo; with the Georgetown Gilbert &amp;amp; Sullivan Society (GG&amp;amp;SS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent shows here in State College have included &amp;ldquo;Oliver!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Sound of Music,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Sweeney Todd,&amp;rdquo; with Singing Onstage, &amp;ldquo;Dracula&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;The Survivor&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Gypsy&amp;rdquo; with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://scctonline.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;State College Community Theatre (SCCT)&lt;/a&gt;, and &amp;ldquo;The Memory of Water&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Harper Regan&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Two Can Play&amp;rdquo; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/thenextstageinc/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Next Stage&lt;/a&gt; theatre company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a former president of SCCT.
I&amp;rsquo;m proud to say that my colleagues and I forced the owners of the Boal Barn to make essential repairs to the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I love to sing and dance.
My wife and daugther are the instrumentalists, but I pick a banjo now and then or play a bit of harmonic or tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I also enjoy volunteering with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://acousticbrew.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Acoustic Brew&lt;/a&gt; concert series and attending shows.
Our folk music friends are pretty awesome, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the spirit moves me, I write poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equipment</title>
      <link>/personal/ham_radio_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/ham_radio_2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;vhf-uhf&#34;&gt;VHF/UHF&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenwood TH-D74 HT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yaesu FT-70DR HT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenwood TM-D710G mobile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenwood TM-281 mobile (for APRS I-Gate)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tytera MD-2017 HT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hf&#34;&gt;HF&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Icom IC-7300&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MFJ 993B autotuner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiband (80-10m) dipole at 10 m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other&#34;&gt;Other&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tecsun PL-880 portable shortwave/medium wave receiver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Openspot UHF digital mode (D-Star, Fusion, DMR) hotspot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ham Radio</title>
      <link>/personal/ham_radio_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/ham_radio_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was licensed as a Tech+ in 1993, but was never really active.
Kids and finishing grad school were higher priorities.
After reading &amp;ldquo;Seveneves,&amp;rdquo; I got the bug again and took both the Technician and General in the space of a couple of weeks in the summer of 2016.
With the moral support of some fellow club members and a helpful Elmer, I upgraded to Extra in July of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy VHF special event support and help run a local EmComm net. I&amp;rsquo;m doing my best to chase DX on 20 and 40 m using a barefoot IC-7300 and a multiband dipole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help with our local APRS coverage, I also run a fill-in digipeater/I-Gate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have ambitions of (re)learning code and doing QRP SOTA and POTA type of activations as a way to combine my love of outdoor activities (hiking, cycling, and paddling) with ham radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My local club is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://http://nittany-arc.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nittany Amateur Radio Club&lt;/a&gt;.
I check-in to the Western PA D-Star net occasionally, and often monitor the 146.85 W3YA repeater and the Yaesu System Fusion AmericaLink reflector.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heroics</title>
      <link>/personal/heroics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/heroics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some rascal or rogue&lt;/br&gt;
Stashed kryptonite&lt;/br&gt;
Upon my person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in that fingertip pocket of my Levi’s,&lt;/br&gt;
Or the underside of the spare button on that green and black plaid shirt,&lt;/br&gt;
Or the tunnel in my underwear that no man uses I assure you but most boys try at least once.&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always loved flying&lt;/br&gt;
And nerdy girls.&lt;/br&gt;
I have been underestimated by villains,&lt;/br&gt;
And see beneath the surfaces of things.&lt;/br&gt;
I’m unusually attentive to phone booths,&lt;/br&gt;
And of course capes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just when I tried to catch bullets&lt;/br&gt;
Lois changed lanes.&lt;/br&gt;
And I needed the horn rims to see up from down&lt;/br&gt;
When forced to discover that&lt;/br&gt;
the laws of gravity&lt;/br&gt;
Are never broken.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public Service</title>
      <link>/personal/public_service/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/personal/public_service/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been involved in local politics, serving as clerk and Judge of Elections in my State College precinct and now Majority Inspector.
I was a moderate Republican at one point, but changed parties after the 2000 election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I were formerly Democratic Precinct Co-chairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m especially proud of the work that led to the construction of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.traillink.com/trail/bellefonte-central-rail-trail/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bellefonte Central Rail Trail&lt;/a&gt;.
It was one of our community&amp;rsquo;s constructive responses to &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;.
Just weeks after the attack, more than 100 volunteers cleared the first overgrown section of railbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently serve on the State College Borough Transportation Commission.
In a previous rotation on the Commission, we helped implement traffic calming speed humps in the Highlands neighborhood, pedestrian lead times in the downtown district, and plan for a set of bike lanes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
