<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ham radio | Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/tag/ham-radio/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/ham-radio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ham radio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>ham radio</title>
      <link>/tag/ham-radio/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ham Radio</title>
      <link>/personal/ham_radio_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/personal/ham_radio_1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was licensed as a Tech+ in 1993, but was never really active.
Kids and finishing grad school were higher priorities.
After reading &amp;ldquo;Seveneves,&amp;rdquo; I got the bug again and took both the Technician and General in the space of a couple of weeks in the summer of 2016.
With the moral support of some fellow club members and a helpful Elmer, I upgraded to Extra in July of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoy VHF special event support and help run a local EmComm net. I&amp;rsquo;m doing my best to chase DX on 20 and 40 m using a barefoot IC-7300 and a multiband doublet.
In the fall of 2019, I added tuned dipoles for 20m and 40m, and in
the Spring of 2020, I added a Comet 3 for better VHF and UHF coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help with our local APRS coverage, I also run a fill-in digipeater/I-Gate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am taking the CW Academy courses to (re)learn the code in hopes of doing QRP SOTA and POTA type of activations.
That seems like an ideal way to combine my love of outdoor activities (hiking, cycling, and paddling) with ham radio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My local club is the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://https://nittany-arc.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nittany Amateur Radio Club&lt;/a&gt;.
I check-in to the Western PA D-Star net occasionally, and often monitor the 146.85 W3YA repeater and the Yaesu System Fusion AmericaLink reflector.
In Spring 2020, I joined the Board of Directors of NARC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, I took over as Faculty Adviser for the Penn State Amateur Radio Club.
I am also trustee for the three K3CR repeaters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
