<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>QSL? QSL</title>
      <link>/post/qsl-qsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/qsl-qsl/</guid>
      <description>Last night, my friend Mike (N3LI) and I made our first-ever CW QSOs. In ham-speak, that means we chatted using Morse code.
It wasn&amp;rsquo;t fast, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t copy each other completely. But we exchanged meaningful information using a classic communication mode that is no longer a requirement for licensing but is still going strong. It was great fun, and we plan to keep practicing and plan to meet-up again next week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New lab logo</title>
      <link>/post/new-lab-logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/new-lab-logo/</guid>
      <description>For I don&amp;rsquo;t remember how many years I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted a lab logo. I thought that designing a logo was something that some student might actually enjoy doing. But I never pushed or insisted, and so it never happened.
Then, as a byproduct of a bunch of reading I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing about causal modeling and the philosophy of science, I came up with a figure that seems to work on several levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building walls and tearing them down</title>
      <link>/post/building-walls-and-tearing-them-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/building-walls-and-tearing-them-down/</guid>
      <description>The building of walls is of much concern these days. This song from Anais Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s folk opera &amp;ldquo;Hadestown&amp;rdquo; sheds light on why some of us want so desperately to build them:
 I must also wonder what future Mexican leader will call on us to tear down the wall we seem so desperate to build?
 Walls are no symbol of strength. They shut in more than they keep out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test-driven development is hard...and important.</title>
      <link>/post/test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been developing an R package that interacts with the Databrary.org API and with Datavyu annotation files stored locally or on Databrary alongside shared videos. If you’re curious, you can download the databraryapi package from this GitHub repository: https://github.com/PLAY-behaviorome/databraryapi.
Like many people in the software world, I’m entirely self-taught. Ok, I took a class in C programming at the U.S. Department of Agriculture’s Graduate School in the year before I applied to graduate schools in cognitive neuroscience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 12:37:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Hi, all.
After a break, I&amp;rsquo;m back to blogging using the blogdown package for R, and the Hugo Academic theme. Let me know what you think.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ending the endless war</title>
      <link>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</guid>
      <description>I find Andrew Sullivan worth reading almost all of the time even if I disagree with him. This time, I agree completely:
 &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;I simply do not believe that the West has the knowledge, the will, or the ability to shape the extremely complicated and endlessly vicious politics of the Middle East. And I defy anyone to show otherwise&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;
 So, while I find the present occupant completely unfit for office, I applaud his announcement to withdraw U.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>