<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing through the fog</title>
      <link>/post/seeing-through-the-fog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/seeing-through-the-fog/</guid>
      <description>I understand why Republican partisans want to confuse the public. But this is crystal clear.
No candidate for elected office in the United States should ever seek or receive help from foreign countries to win an election. Not ever. Period.
In taking office, a president pledges (or affirms) to &amp;ldquo;preserve, protect, and defend the Constitution.&amp;rdquo; Senators and Congressional Representatives pledge (or affirm) to &amp;ldquo;support and defend the Constitution of the United States against all enemies, foreign and domestic&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What makes America great (to me)</title>
      <link>/post/what-makes-america-great-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/what-makes-america-great-to-me/</guid>
      <description>Today I rode my bicycle to our public library (an American innovation), and walked around the corner to an Indian restaurant that is owned and operated by people of Latin American heritage. While I enjoyed a quiet lunch, diners of all ages and multiple backgrounds did the same. There was a head-scarf-wearing mother who works at the restaurant attending to her infant, a separate group of head-scarf-wearing people, people in wheelchairs, people with long hair and short, dark skin and light.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just do it!</title>
      <link>/post/just-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/just-do-it/</guid>
      <description>Two years ago, I participated in my first Field Day as a ham. For the uninitiated, Field Day is an annual event where radio amateurs set-up radio stations in locations they would normally not operate. We then try to make as many contacts as possible in a 24 hour period.
My local club, the Nittany Amateur Radio Club brings out the big guns for Field Day &amp;ndash; big directional beam antennas, high power amplifiers, and capable radios (Elecraft K3S and Icom IC-7610).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is there a crisis of reproducibility in science?</title>
      <link>/post/is-there-a-crisis-of-reproducibility-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/is-there-a-crisis-of-reproducibility-in-science/</guid>
      <description>A recent article in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences by Redish et al. argues that &amp;lsquo;reproducibility failures are essential to scientific inquiry.&amp;rsquo; The authors remind readers that progress in many fields often proceeds haltingly, with successes, retrenchments, reconsiderations, and revisions. As examples, Redish et al. summarize the history of the Four Color Theorem, the claim that Fourier series can characterize any function, and the conditions under which neural networks can carry out certain computations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atheist prayer</title>
      <link>/post/on-gun-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/on-gun-love/</guid>
      <description>we fear the people who love their guns more than we love our children.
the atheist prays every day to gods she finds incomprehensible:
Remove the sticks of destruction from our arsenals and minds. Banish them to eternity. Cleanse us that we may be clean.
a merciful god would hear this supplicant, know her grace,  and answer in the affirmative. a god who loved his children would, she thinks and hopes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devilish details</title>
      <link>/post/devilish-details/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/devilish-details/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself at odds recently with colleagues who, like me, view themselves as advocates for open science. This post attempts to clarify what I see as the crux of our disagreements.
We don&amp;rsquo;t own our data Most researchers feel a strong sense of ownership about our data and often, properly so I think, feel especially protective of our research participants. The fact remains, however, that despite our essential role in determining what data get collected from whom and how, we researchers have the weakest claim to actually owning the data we collect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poets may know it</title>
      <link>/post/poets-may-know-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/poets-may-know-it/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been slowly moving my poetry into position on this site. There may be scraps left in some corner of the hard drive, but the task is essentially done.
There were curious and inexplicable bursts and equally unexplained lapses. Writing could be more of a habit were I more disciplined. Instead, I await the midnight muse. Something in those hours calls forth a form of loose thinking I require to write evocatively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you JS8...</title>
      <link>/post/if-you-js8/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/if-you-js8/</guid>
      <description>One thing I like about ham radio is the variety. There are new modes to try and new things to learn all the time.
Most recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the low power, weak signal JS8Call mode. JS8Call takes the weak signal characteristics of the JT8 mode that has taken the ham world by storm, but enables actual ragchew-style QSOs. This means that with low power, modest antennas, and poor propagation conditions, hams can have actual conversations with one another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Donocrats and Trumpublicans</title>
      <link>/post/of-donocrats-and-trumpublicans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/of-donocrats-and-trumpublicans/</guid>
      <description>I wish it were otherwise, but I agree with Andrew Sullivan. Regardless of what the Mueller report holds, Trump has severely damaged the country and made our Nation weaker, not stronger.
Regretably, Mr. Trump has been exactly the sort of president many of us feared he would be. And his supporters, Donocrat and Trumpublican alike, actually like it that way. That is the grim reality that his opponents must face. His bombast and bluster and poutiness and pettiness appeal to large numbers of Americans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Burns a bridge</title>
      <link>/post/burns-a-bridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/burns-a-bridge/</guid>
      <description>burns a bridge the night long, this heat retards bitterness and cold yellow-red flickers illuminate, but dimly even in that moment fleeting but wonders he later wherefore the stench and who has shut the road again.
we do not swim.
in motion emotion forever  forward fresh, frenetic, pushed by what i know not pulled more like perhaps by gravitational force or some repulsion. the formula admits no closed form solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open developmental science</title>
      <link>/post/open-developmental-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/open-developmental-science/</guid>
      <description>If you plan to attend the Society for Research in Child Development (SRCD) meeting in Baltimore later this week, you might be interested in some of the open science activities that will be taking place:
On Friday, March 22, from 10-11:30 am, I am co-leading a conversation hour on the topic What SRCD is doing to address open science. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on a set of new policies and guidelines to authors that the SRCD Task Force on Scientific Integrity and Openness produced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>April 9: A national day of reflection and reconciliation</title>
      <link>/post/april-9-a-day-of-reflection-and-reconciliation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/april-9-a-day-of-reflection-and-reconciliation/</guid>
      <description>America needs a holiday dedicated to reflecting on the many ways we have failed to meet our founding ideals. We need such a holiday to reconcile the past with our common hopes for a better future, to &amp;lsquo;bind up the Nation&amp;rsquo;s wounds&amp;rsquo;, as Lincoln suggested in his second inaugural address. I suggest we make April 9 that day.
Lee surrendered to Grant on April 9, 1865 in Appomattox Court House, Virginia, a month after Lincoln&amp;rsquo;s second inaugural.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Itsy Bitsy</title>
      <link>/post/itsy-bitsy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/itsy-bitsy/</guid>
      <description>i wonder what it is like
to swing from a rope of my own
making; pulled out of my&amp;hellip;
as it were,
hoping some unsuspecting fly
by night nibbles on the line i&amp;rsquo;ve cast
when patience is more than virtue and cunning no vice</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavior is the linchpin</title>
      <link>/post/behavior-is-the-linchpin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/behavior-is-the-linchpin/</guid>
      <description>The Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute for Child Health and Human Development (NICHD) has requested input on a draft strategic plan for 2020-2024.
NICHD supports Databrary and PLAY, and it has supported my habituation modeling work in the past. The following is a draft response my colleagues and I are working on.
Dear Dr. Bianchi:
Thank you for the opportunity to respond to the NICHD Strategic Plan for Fiscal Years 2020-2024.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In search of the ethogram</title>
      <link>/post/in-search-of-the-ethogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/in-search-of-the-ethogram/</guid>
      <description>Psychology is in part, a science of behavior. Mental experience &amp;ndash; thoughts and feelings &amp;ndash; are also common targets of inquiry.
I recently went looking for a systematic catalogue of behaviors that should, in theory, constitute the substance of what psychologists and other behavioral scientists study. My goal was to take that catalogue as a starting point for thinking about the relationship between information available for perception and the actions (behaviors) that this information informs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameters for action</title>
      <link>/post/parameters-for-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/parameters-for-action/</guid>
      <description>Several years ago, Florian Raudies, Swapnaa Jayaraman and I published a paper where we simulated the optic flow that infants would experience in different head/body postures. We computed cyclopian (one-eyed) flow on the basis of this schematic:
Here, the key parameters were the instantaneous translation \((v_x{}, v_y{}, v_z{})\) and rotation \((\omega_{x}, \omega_y{}, \omega_z{})\) of the planar retina. Coupled with the optic flow equation,
\(\begin{pmatrix}\dot{x} \\ \dot{y}\end{pmatrix}=\frac{1}{z} \begin{pmatrix}-f &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; x\\ 0 &amp;amp; -f &amp;amp; y \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix}{v_x{}}\\ {v_y{}} \\{v_z{}}\end{pmatrix}+ \frac{1}{f} \begin{pmatrix} xy &amp;amp; -(f^2+x^2) &amp;amp; fy\\ f^2+y^2 &amp;amp; -xy &amp;amp; -fy \end{pmatrix} \begin{pmatrix} \omega_{x}\\ \omega_{y}\\ \omega_{z} \end{pmatrix}\)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The webs we weave</title>
      <link>/post/the-webs-we-weave/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-webs-we-weave/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been ‘sketching’ out conceptual models for some time without realizing that there is an entire field of analysis where these sorts of diagrams are the starting point: Causal modeling. My introduction to this world was Judea Pearl’s The Book of Why: The New Science of Cause and Effect. Interested casual readers might also enjoy Steve Sloman’s excellent and delightfully clear Causal Models: How People Think About the World and Its Alternatives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QSL? QSL</title>
      <link>/post/qsl-qsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/qsl-qsl/</guid>
      <description>Last night, my friend Mike (N3LI) and I made our first-ever CW QSOs. In ham-speak, that means we chatted using Morse code.
It wasn&amp;rsquo;t fast, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t copy each other completely. But we exchanged meaningful information using a classic communication mode that is no longer a requirement for licensing but is still going strong. It was great fun, and we plan to keep practicing and plan to meet-up again next week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New lab logo</title>
      <link>/post/new-lab-logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/new-lab-logo/</guid>
      <description>For I don&amp;rsquo;t remember how many years I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted a lab logo. I thought that designing a logo was something that some student might actually enjoy doing. But I never pushed or insisted, and so it never happened.
Then, as a byproduct of a bunch of reading I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing about causal modeling and the philosophy of science, I came up with a figure that seems to work on several levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building walls and tearing them down</title>
      <link>/post/building-walls-and-tearing-them-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/building-walls-and-tearing-them-down/</guid>
      <description>The building of walls is of much concern these days. This song from Anais Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s folk opera &amp;ldquo;Hadestown&amp;rdquo; sheds light on why some of us want so desperately to build them:
 I must also wonder what future Mexican leader will call on us to tear down the wall we seem so desperate to build?
 Walls are no symbol of strength. They shut in more than they keep out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test-driven development is hard...and important.</title>
      <link>/post/test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/test-driven-development-is-hard-and-important/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been developing an R package that interacts with the Databrary.org API and with Datavyu annotation files stored locally or on Databrary alongside shared videos. If you’re curious, you can download the databraryapi package from this GitHub repository: https://github.com/PLAY-behaviorome/databraryapi.
Like many people in the software world, I’m entirely self-taught. Ok, I took a class in C programming at the U.S. Department of Agriculture’s Graduate School in the year before I applied to graduate schools in cognitive neuroscience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 12:37:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m back to blogging using Hugo and the Academic theme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ending the endless war</title>
      <link>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</guid>
      <description>I find Andrew Sullivan worth reading almost all of the time even if I disagree with him. This time, I agree completely:
 &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;I simply do not believe that the West has the knowledge, the will, or the ability to shape the extremely complicated and endlessly vicious politics of the Middle East. And I defy anyone to show otherwise&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;
 So, while I find the present occupant completely unfit for office, I applaud his announcement to withdraw U.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>