<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>open science on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/categories/open-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in open science on Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/open-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Devilish details</title>
      <link>/post/devilish-details/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/devilish-details/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself at odds recently with colleagues who, like me, view themselves as advocates for open science. This post attempts to clarify what I see as the crux of our disagreements.
We don&amp;rsquo;t own our data Most researchers feel a strong sense of ownership about our data and often, properly so I think, feel especially protective of our research participants. The fact remains, however, that despite our essential role in determining what data get collected from whom and how, we researchers have the weakest claim to actually owning the data we collect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open developmental science</title>
      <link>/post/open-developmental-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/open-developmental-science/</guid>
      <description>If you plan to attend the Society for Research in Child Development (SRCD) meeting in Baltimore later this week, you might be interested in some of the open science activities that will be taking place:
On Friday, March 22, from 10-11:30 am, I am co-leading a conversation hour on the topic What SRCD is doing to address open science. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on a set of new policies and guidelines to authors that the SRCD Task Force on Scientific Integrity and Openness produced.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>