<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ham radio | Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/category/ham-radio/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/ham-radio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ham radio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>ham radio</title>
      <link>/category/ham-radio/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just do it!</title>
      <link>/post/just-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/just-do-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I participated in my first Field Day as a ham.
For the uninitiated, Field Day is an annual event where radio amateurs set-up radio stations in locations they would normally not operate.
We then try to make as many contacts as possible in a 24 hour period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My local club, the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nittany-arc.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nittany Amateur Radio Club&lt;/a&gt; brings out the big guns for Field Day &amp;ndash; big directional beam antennas, high power amplifiers, and capable radios (Elecraft K3S and Icom IC-7610).
This year was no exception.
Here are a few pics I took early Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/6m-moon.jpg&#34; width=300px/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/vhf-uhf.jpg&#34; width=300px/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../yagis-fd-2019.jpg&#34; height=480px/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike two years ago, when one of the more senior hams had to shove the microphone and headphones into my hands to get me to jump into the chair, this year I happily jumped into the fray whenever the opportunity arose.
And that would include 3 am on Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I&amp;rsquo;m not alone in seeing an experienced ham work a pile-up and think how could I possibly listen, type, and talk in the phonetic alphabet without losing it.
And the answer is, like so many other things, you just have to try.
So, my unsolicited advice to hams like me who are a little mic shy, or maybe intimidated by CW?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just do it.
It&amp;rsquo;s exhilarating to jump out of your comfort zone and piles of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, some afternoons you can &amp;lsquo;work&amp;rsquo; (talk to) people in Greenland with 100 Watts and a wire strung up between the trees in your backyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;73 de K3ROG&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you JS8...</title>
      <link>/post/if-you-js8/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/if-you-js8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One thing I like about ham radio is the variety.
There are new modes to try and new things to learn all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the low power, weak signal 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://js8call.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;JS8Call mode&lt;/a&gt;.
JS8Call takes the weak signal characteristics of the JT8 mode that has taken the ham world by storm, but enables actual ragchew-style QSOs.
This means that with low power, modest antennas, and poor propagation conditions, hams can have actual conversations with one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This represents a significant departure from FT8 where callsigns, grid squares, and signal reports are about all that get exchanged.
I&amp;rsquo;ve played around with JT8, too, but the appeal seems limited to me.
Yes, my elmer got DXCC on FT8 in less than a month, and yes, I&amp;rsquo;m still working my way there on SSB.
But, JS8Call suits my interests more directly.
The developer, a guy named Jordan Scherer is an open source guru and all around righteous ham, and he has a plan about where this sort of tool might go.
Check out this 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/mZKhVcFOljY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; to see what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how my 25 W signal was getting out earlier today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/js8call-k3rog.jpg&#34;/&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QSL? QSL</title>
      <link>/post/qsl-qsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/qsl-qsl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last night, my friend Mike (N3LI) and I made our first-ever CW QSOs.
In ham-speak, that means we chatted using Morse code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t fast, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t copy each other completely.
But we exchanged meaningful information using a classic communication mode that is no longer a requirement for licensing but is still going strong.
It was great fun, and we plan to keep practicing and plan to meet-up again next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-learning Morse code has reinforced several things for me.
Patience and persistence are the most important qualities for long-term mastery of any difficult skill.
And it&amp;rsquo;s good to give older brains a tough, but realizable challenge.
Especially when there are concrete and visible measures of success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So any no-code hams out there who haven&amp;rsquo;t taken the plunge, come on in!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
