<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>politics | Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/category/politics/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>politics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>politics</title>
      <link>/category/politics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing through the fog</title>
      <link>/post/seeing-through-the-fog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/seeing-through-the-fog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I understand why Republican partisans want to confuse the public.
But this is crystal clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No candidate for elected office in the United States should &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt; seek or receive help from foreign countries to win an election.
Not ever.
Period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In taking office, a president pledges (or affirms) to &amp;ldquo;preserve, protect, and defend the Constitution.&amp;rdquo;
Senators and Congressional Representatives pledge (or affirm) to &amp;ldquo;support and defend the Constitution of the United States against all enemies, foreign and domestic&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has now at least twice asked for help from a foreign power to gain political advantage over an opponent, once as a candidate, and at least once as president.
The asking itself is unmistakably, incontrovertibly, and indefensibly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking foreign interference subverts the integrity of our elections, undermines the Constitution, and violates the presidential oath of office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A president must uphold the rule of law not advance the law of rulers.
He is unfit.
He must be impeached and removed from office.
Failing to do so represents a violation of the oath of office taken by Senators and Representatives alike to &amp;ldquo;defend the Constitution against all enemies, foreign and domestic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no fog here, just strategically and cynically blown smoke.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atheist prayer</title>
      <link>/post/on-gun-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/on-gun-love/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;we fear the people who love their guns&lt;/br&gt;
more than we love our children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the atheist prays every day to gods she finds incomprehensible:&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove the sticks of destruction&lt;/br&gt;
from our arsenals and minds.&lt;/br&gt;
Banish them to eternity.&lt;/br&gt;
Cleanse us that we may be clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a merciful god would hear this supplicant,&lt;/br&gt;
know her grace, &lt;/br&gt;
and answer in the affirmative.&lt;/br&gt;
a god who loved his children&lt;/br&gt;
would, she thinks and hopes.&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but we could surely find other ways of killing, you object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yes, I acknowledge,&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or perhaps&lt;/br&gt;
just perhaps&lt;/br&gt;
choose not to.&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Donocrats and Trumpublicans</title>
      <link>/post/of-donocrats-and-trumpublicans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/of-donocrats-and-trumpublicans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wish it were otherwise, but I agree with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2019/03/trump-is-a-massive-failure-and-getting-exactly-what-he-wants.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andrew Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;.
Regardless of what the Mueller report holds, Trump has severely damaged the country and made our Nation weaker, not stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regretably, Mr. Trump has been exactly the sort of president many of us feared he would be.
And his supporters, Donocrat and Trumpublican alike, actually like it that way.
That is the grim reality that his opponents must face.
His bombast and bluster and poutiness and pettiness appeal to large numbers of Americans.
This charlatan&amp;rsquo;s charlatan seems authentic to them in ways that other more competent and legitimate leaders do not.
Absent a meaningful challenge from within his own party, nowhere evident, that sentiment is unlikely to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/18/opinion/the-right-way-to-resist-trump.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this essay in the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; published before the dust of the 2016 election had truly settled.
Zingales argues that opponents of Italy&amp;rsquo;s Trump-like prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, learned the hard way that the only way to defeat a larger-than-life autocrat is to sweat the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Italian experience provides a blueprint for how to defeat Mr. Trump. Only two men in Italy have won an electoral competition against Mr. Berlusconi: Romano Prodi and the current prime minister, Matteo Renzi (albeit only in a 2014 European election). Both of them treated Mr. Berlusconi as an ordinary opponent. They focused on the issues, not on his character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deficit has exploded, the border is insecure, North Korea remains a mortal threat to its neighbors, America&amp;rsquo;s reputation, power, and influence have declined, the rule of law has been weakened, and we have magnified the already challenges we must inevitably face in responding to climate change.
Trump has not, will not, and cannot make America great.
And his supporters have not, will not, and cannot acknowledge it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/john_adams_134175&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Adams said&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Facts are stubborn things; and whatever may be our wishes, our inclinations, or the dictates of our passions, they cannot alter the state of facts and evidence.&amp;rdquo;
And it is the facts and evidence of Trump&amp;rsquo;s incompetence we must highlight, relentlessly and fearlessly, to defeat him.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>April 9: A national day of reflection and reconciliation</title>
      <link>/post/april-9-a-day-of-reflection-and-reconciliation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/april-9-a-day-of-reflection-and-reconciliation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;America needs a holiday dedicated to reflecting on the many ways we have failed to meet our founding ideals.
We need such a holiday to reconcile the past with our common hopes for a better future, to &amp;lsquo;bind up the Nation&amp;rsquo;s wounds&amp;rsquo;, as Lincoln suggested in his 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_Lincoln%27s_second_inaugural_address&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;second inaugural address&lt;/a&gt;.
I suggest we make April 9 that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee surrendered to Grant on April 9, 1865 in Appomattox Court House, Virginia, a month after Lincoln&amp;rsquo;s second inaugural.
This ended the military portion of the Civil War, the bloodiest conflict in American history.
But in a very real sense, the conflict never truly ended.
It simply shifted to other battlefields, several of which rage on today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the American project is stronger when we, the people, view our history openly and honestly, with the courage to acknowledge our shortcomings.
Indeed, lacking such an honest accounting, our sense of pride may appear prideful or worse, willfully ignorant of the price so many have paid for this progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where and how has America fallen short?
My list may differ from yours, but here are some suggestions: Our genocide of Native Americans, our history of slavery, our treatment of any number of immigrant groups, the long delay in granting women suffrage, the Japanese internment, the ways 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/04/adam-serwer-madison-grant-white-nationalism/583258/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American white supremacists inspired the Nazis&lt;/a&gt;, the interminable war on terror no one seems willing to end, and our failures to confront and address climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A truly great and powerful nation can muster the courage to face its own flaws and to hold itself account.
Indeed, lacking that courage, how can any people aspire to righteousness or assume the responsibilities of leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Jews, who atone for sin on Yom Kippur by seeking forgiveness from one another before facing judgment from the almighty, let us set aside April 9 for a national day of reflection and reconciliation.
Let us find strength in examining our weakness.
And let such a day form a more perfect union among us that we may secure the blessings of liberty, as we the people have ordained in our Constitution, for all posterity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ending the endless war</title>
      <link>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ending-the-endless-war/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I find Andrew Sullivan worth reading almost all of the time even if I disagree with him.
This 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/12/andrew-sullivan-establishment-will-never-say-no-to-a-war.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;time&lt;/a&gt;, I agree completely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;I simply do not believe that the West has the knowledge, the will, or the ability to shape the extremely complicated and endlessly vicious politics of the Middle East. And I defy anyone to show otherwise&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while I find the present occupant completely unfit for office, I applaud his announcement to withdraw U.S. troops from Syria and reduce our presence in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We forget that &lt;em&gt;Congress&lt;/em&gt; has the Constitutional power to declare war or decisively choose not to.
It&amp;rsquo;s part of the balance of powers created by the Framers.
I&amp;rsquo;d like to see Congress restore balance here and in other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
