<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>impeachment | Rick Gilmore&#39;s site</title>
    <link>/tag/impeachment/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/impeachment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>impeachment</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>impeachment</title>
      <link>/tag/impeachment/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is great</title>
      <link>/post/this-is-great/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/this-is-great/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Perhaps like me you suspected that the red hats did not share your view of what makes America great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ERIbhsCzZwk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know the depth of that disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the methodical and patriotic work of the House impeachment managers, we know in terrifying detail how much worse 1/6 might have become. Already there were casualties, among mobsters and law enforcement alike, shot, bludgeoned, or crushed to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue lives matter, except of course when they do not. Especially when their loss does not fit an expedient narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rbukVhEih58&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These unconscionable acts of aggression against the foundations of our democracy by leaders and citizens alike are great only to tyrants and knaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frum has observed that 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/02/there-is-no-defenseonly-complicity/617996/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;complicity&lt;/a&gt; or conviction are the only choices for senators terrified of the beast their cowardice has created. Will worries that only 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/will-senate-republicans-allow-their-louts-to-rule-the-party/2021/02/11/ce082db6-6caf-11eb-9ead-673168d5b874_story.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;louts&lt;/a&gt; will remain in a party perhaps once grand but no longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worry that senators will soon choose what vision of greatness they endorse and not enough will choose wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing through the fog</title>
      <link>/post/seeing-through-the-fog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/seeing-through-the-fog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I understand why Republican partisans want to confuse the public.
But this is crystal clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No candidate for elected office in the United States should &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt; seek or receive help from foreign countries to win an election.
Not ever.
Period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In taking office, a president pledges (or affirms) to &amp;ldquo;preserve, protect, and defend the Constitution.&amp;rdquo;
Senators and Congressional Representatives pledge (or affirm) to &amp;ldquo;support and defend the Constitution of the United States against all enemies, foreign and domestic&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has now at least twice asked for help from a foreign power to gain political advantage over an opponent, once as a candidate, and at least once as president.
The asking itself is unmistakably, incontrovertibly, and indefensibly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking foreign interference subverts the integrity of our elections, undermines the Constitution, and violates the presidential oath of office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A president must uphold the rule of law not advance the law of rulers.
He is unfit.
He must be impeached and removed from office.
Failing to do so represents a violation of the oath of office taken by Senators and Representatives alike to &amp;ldquo;defend the Constitution against all enemies, foreign and domestic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no fog here, just strategically and cynically blown smoke.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
